[Music]
Reedman
reads the Giver by Lois Lowry narrated by Fraser Reedman chapter
10 "I go in here, Jonas F told them when they reached the front door of the House
of the Old after parking their bicycles in the designated area.
"I don't know why I'm nervous," she confessed been here so often
before." She turned her folder over in her hands. "Well, everything's different now,"
Jonas reminded her. "Even the name plates on our bikes,"
Fiona laughed. During the night the name plate of each new 12 had been removed by
the Maintenance Crew and replaced with a style that indicated citizen in training
I don't want to be late," she said hastily, and started up the
steps. "If we finish at the same time, I'll ride home with
you." Jonas nodded, waved to her, and headed around the building towards the Annex
the small wing attached to the back. He certainly didn't want to be late
for his first day of training, either. The Annex was very ordinary, its door
unremarkable. He reached with a heavy handle, then noticed a buzzer on the wall.
So he buzzed instead. "Yes?" The voice came through a small speaker above the buzzer.
"It's, uh, Jonas. I'm the new— —I mean—" "Come in."
A click indicated that the door had been unlatched. The lobby was very small and
contained only a desk at which a female Attendant sat working on some papers. She
looked up when he entered; then, to his surprise, she stood.
It was a small thing with standing; but no one had ever stood automatically to
acknowledge Jonas's presence before. "Welcome, Receiver of Memory," she
said respectfully. "Oh, please," he replied uncomfortably. "Call me
Jonas." She smiled, pushed a button, and he heard a click that unlocked the door to her
left. "You may go right on in," she told him. Then she seemed to notice his
discomfort and to realize I its origin.
No doors in the community were locked, ever. None that Jonas knew of, anyway. "The
locks are simply to ensure The Receiver's privacy because he needs
concentration," she explained. "It would be difficult if citizens wandered in,
looking for the Department of Bicycle Repair, or something." Jonas laughed, relaxing a
little. The woman seemed very friendly, and it was true— —in fact it was a joke
throughout the community— —that the Department of Bicycle Repair and
unimportant little office, was relocated so often that no one ever knew where it
was there's nothing dangerous here," she told him. "But," she added, glancing at the
wall clock, "he doesn't like to be kept waiting." Jonas hurried through the door
and found himself in a comfortably furnished living area was not unlike his own family in his
dwelling. Furniture was standard throughout the community: practical,
sturdy, the function of each piece clearly defined. A bed for sleeping. A
table for eating. A desk for studying. All of those things were in this spacious
room, though each was slightly different from those in his own
dwelling. The fabrics on the upholstered chairs and sofa were slightly thicker
and more luxurious; the table legs were not straight like those at home, but
slender and curved, with a small carved decoration at the
foot. The bed, in an alve at the far end of the room, was draped with a splendid
cloth embroidered over its entire surface with intricate designs the most
conspicuous difference was the books. In his own dwelling, there were the
necessary reference volumes that each household contained: a dictionary, and the thick community
volume which contains descriptions of every office, factory, building, and
committee. And the Book of Rules, of course. The books in his own dwelling
were the only books that Jonas had ever seen. He had never known that other books existed.
But this room's walls were completely covered by bookcases, filled, which reached to the
ceiling must have been hundreds— —perhaps thousands— —of books, their titles embossed
in shiny letters Jonah stared at them you couldn't imagine what the thousands of pages
contained. Could there be rules beyond the rules that govern the community?
Could there be more descriptions of offices and factories and committees? He
had only a second to look around because he was aware that the man sitting in a
chair beside the table was watching him. Hastily he moved forward, stood
before the man, bowed slightly, and said, "I'm Jonas." "I know. Welcome, Receiver of
Memory jonus recognized the man. He was the Elder who had seemed
separate from the others at the Ceremony, though he was dressed in the same
special clothing that only Elders wore. Jonas looked self-consciously into
the pale eyes that mirrored his own. "Sir, I apologize for my lack of
understanding...." He waited, but the man did not give the standard accepting of
apology response. After a moment, Jonas went on, "But I thought— —I mean I think, he
corrected, reminding himself that if precision of language were ever to be
important, it was certainly important now, in the presence of this
man, "that you are the receiver of Memory.
I'm only, well, I was only assigned, I mean selected, yesterday. I'm not anything at all. Not
yet." The man looked at him thoughtfully, silently. It was a look that combined
interest, curiosity, concern, and perhaps a little sympathy as well. Finally he
spoke. "Beginning today, this moment, at least to me, you are The
Receiver. "I have been Receiver for a long time. A very, very long time. You can see
that, can't you?" Jonas nodded. The man was wrinkled, and his eyes, though piercing in their
unusual lightness, seemed tired. The flesh around them was darkened into shadowed
circles. "I can see that you are very old," Jonas responded with respect. The Old
were always given the highest respect. The man smiled. He touched the sagging flesh on
his own face with amusement. "I am not, actually, as old as I look," he told
Jonas. "This job has aged me. I know I look as if I should be scheduled for release
very soon. But actually I have a good deal of time
left. "I was pleased, though, when you were selected. It took them a long
time. The failure of the previous selection was 10 years ago, and my energy is starting to
diminish. I need what strength I have remaining for your training. We have hard and painful work
to do, you and I. "Please sit down," he said, and gestured toward the nearby
chair. Jonas lowered himself onto the soft cushion seat. The man closed his eyes and continued
speaking. "When I became a 12 I was selected, as you were. I was
frightened, as I'm sure you are."
He opened his eyes for a moment and peered at Jonas, who nodded. The eyes closed
again. "I came to this very room to begin my training. It was such a long time
ago. "The previous Receiver seemed just as
old to me as I do to you. He was just as tired as I am
today." He sat forward suddenly, opened his eyes, and said, "You may ask questions. I
have so little experience in describing this process. It is forbidden to talk of
it." "I know, sir. I have read the instructions," Jonas
said. "So I may neglect to make things as clear as I should." The man chuckled. "My
job is important and has enormous honor.
But that does not mean I am perfect, and when I tried before to train a successor, I
failed. Please ask any questions that will help you."
In his mind, Jonas had questions. A thousand. A million questions. As many
questions as there were books lining the walls. But he did not ask one, not
yet. The man sighed, seeming to put his thoughts in order. Then he spoke again.
"Simply stated," he said, "although it's not really simple at
all, my job is to transmit to you all the memories I have within me. Memories of the
past." "Sir Jonah said tentatively, "I be very interested to hear the story of
your life, and to listen to your memories. "I apologize for interrupting," he
added quickly. The man waved his hand impatiently. "No apologies in this room. We haven't
time." "Well," Jonas went on, uncomfortably aware that he might be interrupting
again, "I am really interested, I don't mean that I'm not. But I don't exactly
understand why it's so important. I could do some adult job in
the community, and in my recreation time I could come and listen to the stories from your
childhood I like that. Actually," he added, "I've done that already, in the House of
the Old. The Old like to tell about their childhoods, and it's always fun to
listen." The man shook his head. "No, no," he said. "I'm not being
clear. It's not my past, not my childhood that I must transmit to you." He leaned
back, resting his head against the back of the upholstered
chair. "It's the memories of the whole world," he said with a sigh. "Before you,
before me, before the previous Receiver, and generations before him." Jonas
frowned. "The whole world?" he asked. "I don't understand. Do you mean not
just us? Not just the community? Do you mean Elsewhere,
too?" He tried, in his mind, to grasp the concept. "I'm sorry, sir. I don't understand
exactly. Maybe I'm not smart enough. I don't know what you mean when you say
'the whole world' or 'generations before him.' I thought there was only us. I
thought there was only now." "There's much more. There's all that
goes beyond— —all that is Elsewhere— —and all that goes back, and back back and
back. I received all those, when I was selected. And here in this room, all
alone, I re-experience them again and again. It is how wisdom comes. And how we shape our
future." He rested for a moment, breathing deeply. "I am so weighted with them," he
said. Jonas felt a terrible concern for the man, suddenly. "It's as if..." The man
paused, seeming to search his mind for the right words of description. "It's like going downhill
through deep snow on a sled," he said, finally. "At first it's exhilarating: the
speed; the sharp, clear air; but then the snow accumulates, builds up on the
runners, and you slow, you have to push hard to keep going,
and—" He shook his head suddenly, and peered at Jonas.
"That meant nothing to you, did it?" he asked. Jonas was confused. "I didn't understand it,
sir." "Of course you did You don't know what snow is, do
you?" Jonas shook his head. "Or sled?
Runners?" "No, sir," Jonas said. "Downhill? The term means nothing to you?" "Nothing,
sir." "Well, it's a place to start start. I'd been wondering how to
begin. Move to the bed, and lie face down.
Remove your tunic first." Jonas did so, a little apprehensively. Beneath his bare chest, he
felt the soft folds of the magnificent cloth that covered the
bed. He watched as the man rose and moved first to the wall where the speaker
was. It was the same sort of speaker that occupied a place in every dwelling, but
one thing about it was different.
This one had a switch, which the man deafly snapped to the end that said OFF.
Jonas almost gasped aloud. To have the power to turn the
speaker off! It was an astonishing thing.
Then the man moved with surprising quickness to the corner where the bed
was. He sat on a chair beside Jonas, who was motionless, waiting for what would
happen next. "Close your eyes. Relax. This will not be painful Jonah remembered that he was
allowed, that he had even been encouraged, to ask questions. "What are you going to do, sir?"
he asked, hoping that his voice didn't betray his nervousness. "I am going to transmit the
memory of snow," the old man said, and placed his hands on Jonas's bare back
[Music]